欢迎来到这门关于编译器的课程, 我的名字是Alex Aiken, 我任教于
Welcome to this course on compilers. My name is Alex Aiken. I'm a professor here
斯坦福大学, 我们将要讨论的是如何实现
at Stanford University. And we're going to be talking about the implementation of
编程语言。有两种主要的方法来实现
programming languages. There are two major approaches to implementing
编程语言、编译器和解释器。现在, 这门课主要是
programming languages, compilers, and interpreters. Now, this class is mostly
关于编译器, 但是, 在第一讲，我想先聊聊解释器。
about compilers. But, I do want to say a few words about interpreters here in the
解释器会做什么呢, 我先画一个
first lecture. So, what does an interpreter do? Well, I'm gonna draw a
图在这里, 这个方框是解释器, 我用一个大的 I 作为它的标签
picture here, this box is the interpreter, and it takes, let me label it with a big
它接受的输入是，你写的程序, 以及运行你程序所需的任意数据
I, it takes as input, your program. That you wrote, And, whatever data that you
它直接产生输出, 也就是说
want to run the program on. And it produces the output directly. Meaning that
它在你的程序处理输入数据之前，不会对程序进行任何处理
it doesn't do any processing of the program before it executes it on the input,
所以你只需要写程序, 然后在数据上调用解释器,
So you just write the program, and you invoke the interpreter on the data,
这个程序马上就开始运行了, 所以, 我们可以说
and the program immediately begins running. And so, we can say that the
解释器是在线的, 这意味着它所做的工作包括运行该程序的所有环节
interpreter is, is online, meaning it the work that it does is all part of running your program.
而编译器的结构是不同的, 我们可以画一个图
Now a compiler is structured differently. So, we can draw a picture here.
我们用大写的C来标记编译器, 编译器只接受
Which we'll label with a big C, for the compiler, And the compiler takes as
你的程序作为输入, 然后它产生一个可执行文件。这个
input just your program. And then it produces an executable. And this
可执行文件是另一个程序, 可能是汇编语言, 它可能是字节码。
executable is another program, might be assembly language, it might be bytecode.
它可以是由任意的语言写就的, 但是现在可以
It could be in any number of different implementation languages. But now this can
在你的数据上独立运行, 并会产生输出。 ok，所以
be run separately on your data. And that will produce the output. Okay? And so in
这种结构的编译器是离线的, 这意味着我们首先对程序进行预处理。
this structure the compiler is offline, Meaning that we pre-process the program first.
这个编译器本质上是一个预处理步骤，生成
The compiler is essentially a pre-processing step that produces the
可执行文件, 然后我们可以运行同一个可执行文件，来处理许多不同的输入,
executable, and then we can run that same executable on many, many different inputs,
处理许多不同的数据集，而不需要对这个程序重新编译或做任何其他的处理。
on many different data sets without having to recompile or do any other processing of the program.
我认为给大家介绍一下这个历程是很有帮助的
I think it's helpful to give a little bit of history about
这个关于编译器和解释器最初如何被开发的历程。所以故事开始于
how compilers and interpreters were first developed. So the story begins in the
20世纪50年代, 特别是IBM制造的704台机器, 这是
1950s and in particular with a machine called the 704 built by IBM. This was
这是他们的第一个商业上成功的机器, 尽管有一些
their first commercially successful machine, although there had been some
他们尝试过的早期机器, 但不管怎样, 有趣的是
earlier machines that they had tried out. But anyway the interesting thing about the 704,
一旦顾客开始购买并使用它, 他们就会发现
well, once customers started buying it and using it, is that they found that the
软件成本超过了硬件成本, 而且不仅仅是一点点, 而是
software costs exceeded the hardware costs. And not just by a little bit, but
很多时候, 这很重要, 因为这段时间的硬件
by a lot And, This is important because these, the hardware in these, those days
是极端昂贵的, 即使是在硬件成本最高的时候
was extremely expensive. And even then when hardware cost the most in absolute and relative terms,
比它们以后任何时候都贵, 软件已经
more than they would ever cost again, already the software was
占据花费的主导地位, 从而把计算机的功效发挥到极致, 这导致了
the dominant expense in, in making good use out of computers. And this led
很多人思考如何更好地编写软件。
a number of people to think about how they could do a better job of writing software.
他们如何能够使编程更有成效。刚开始的尝试，
How they could make programming more productive. Where the earliest efforts
用于提高编程的效率，被称为「速度编码」, 开发于1953年
to improve the productivity of programming was called speed coding, developed in 1953
作者是 John Backus, 现在, 速度编码就是我们今天所说的, 一个解释器的早期实现。
by John Backus. Now, speed coding is what we call today, an early example of an interpreter
和其他所有解释器一样，它有一些优点和缺点。
And like all interpreters, it had some advantages and disadvantages.
主要的优势是, 开发程序要快得多, 所以,
The primary advantage was that it was much faster, to develop the programs. So the,
从这个意义上说, 程序员的工作效率更高, 但在其中的缺点之一，
in that sense, the programmer was much more productive, But among its disadvantages,
编写的代码, 速度代码程序相比手写代码要慢10到20倍，
code written, speed code programs were ten to twenty times slower than handwritten programs
这也适用于今天的基于解释器的程序, 如果
and that's also true of interpreted programs today. So if
你有一个使用解释器的实现, 它们将会显著地
you have an implementation that uses an interpreter, they're going to be much
慢于基于编译器或手工编写的代码, 而且速度代码
slower than either a compiler or writing code by hand. And also, the speed code
解释器占用了300字节的内存, 这看起来好像不多。
interpreter took up, 300 bytes of memory. And that doesn't seem like very much.
事实上, 300字节, 今天看起来是一个非常小的程序, 但是在那个时期
In fact, 300 bytes, today, would seem like an incredibly tiny, program. But in those days
你得心里有数, 这是那台机器上30%的内存
you have to keep in mind, that this was 30 Percent Of the memory on the machine
这是704的全部内存的30%，所以
So this was 30 percent of the entire memory of the 704. And so the
解释器占用的内存空间数量本身就是一个问题。尽管速度编码
amount of space that the interpreter took up was itself a concern. Now speed coding
没有被广泛接受, 但是John Backus认为这是有希望的并且给了他
did not become popular, but John Backus thought it was promising and it gave him
关于另一个项目的想法, 当时最重要的应用是
the idea for another project. The most important applications in those days were
科学计算, 程序员想到的是写下公式
scientific computations, and programmers thought in terms of writing down formulas
这是机器可以执行的一种形式, John 认为
in a form that the machine could execute. John thought that the problem with speed
速度编码的问题是这些公式实际上是被解释，他想如果首先
speed coding was that the formulas were in fact interpreted and he thought if first the
将公式被翻译成机器可以直接执行的形式，那样
formulas were translated in to a form that the machine could execute directly, that
代码会更快, 同时仍然允许程序员编写
the code would be faster, And while still allowing the programmer to write the, the,
更高抽象层次的程序, 因此是「公式翻译项目」或
the programs at a high level, and thus was the Formula Translation Project or
FORTRAN项目诞生了。FORTRAN项目执行于1954年到1957年, 有趣的是, 他们认为
FORTRAN Project born. Now FORTRAN ran from 1954 To 1957, And interestingly, they thought it
只需要一年的时间来编译编译器, 但最终花了三年。
would only take them one year to build the compiler but it would end up taking three.
就像今天, 他们不太擅长预测软件项目的时间
So just like today, they weren't very good at predicting how long software projects would take.
但这是一个非常成功的项目, 到1958年, 超过50%的
But it was a very successful project. By 1958, over 50 percent of all
代码是用FORTRAN编写的, 所以50%的程序都是用FORTRAN编写的,
code was written in FORTRAN. So 50 percent of programs were in FORTRAN, And,
对新技术来说是非常快的接纳速度。即便是今天我们也会对这样的成就感到很高兴，
that is very rapid adoption of a new technology. We would be happy with that kind of success today,
所以显然在那个时候他们欣喜若狂, 每个人都认为
and of course at that time they were ecstatic, And everybody thought
这个FORTRAN既提高了抽象层次, 也提高了程序员的生产力
that FORTRAN both raised the level of abstraction, improved programmer productivity
让每个人都能更好地利用这些机器。
and allowed everyone to make much better use of these machines. So
FORTRAN语言是第一个成功的高级语言，它产生了巨大的影响
FORTRAN one was the first successful high level language and it had a huge impact on
特别是计算机科学。特别地，它引出了大量的理论工作。
computer science. In particular, it led to an enormous body of theoretical work. And
编程语言的一个有趣之处是
one of the interesting things about programming languages, actually, is the
结合了理论和实践，因为不太可能
combination of theory and practice. because it's not really possible
在编程语言领域做出好成果，但又没有很好地掌握
in programming languages to do a good job without having both a, a very good grasp
深入的理论和良好工程技能。所以有很多
of fairly deep theory and also good engineering skills. So there's a lot of
非常好的编程语言的系统构建材料，并且通常这
very good systems building material in programming languages and typically it
涉及到一个非常微妙和富有成果的与理论的互动, 所以, 这是
involves a very subtle and fruitful interaction with theory. And so, and this
我认为最吸引人的地方之一，在
is one of the things, I think, that's most attractive about the area's
学习计算机科学这个主题下。而FORTRAN的影响不仅仅是在
the subject of studying computer science. And the impact of FORTRAN was not just on
计算机科学研究方面，当然也在开发实用的编译器方面。
computer science research, of course, but also on the development of, practical compilers.
事实上, 它的影响是如此深远, 以至于今天, 自动编译器仍然
And, in fact, its influence was so profound, that today, auto compilers still
保存FORTRAN语言的轮廓。那么FORTRAN语言的结构是什么？
preserve the outlines of FORTRAN one. So what was the structure of FORTRAN one?
它包含了五个阶段，词法分析和解析, 它们一起
Well it consists five phases lexical analysis and parsing, which together take
专注于语言的句法方面, 语义分析,
care of the syntactic aspects of the language, semantic analysis, which,
显然是更多地关注语义方面, 比如类型和作用域
of course, takes care of more semantic aspects, things like types and scope
规则, 优化, 它是一个对程序的变换集合
rules. Optimization, Which is a collection of transformations on the program to
要么让它运行得更快, 要么使用更少的内存, 最后是代码生成，
either make it run faster or use less memory. And finally code generation which
实际上是翻译到另一个层次, 根据我们的目标,
actually does the translation to another generation. And depending on our goals,
这个翻译可能是到机器码, 可能是到一个虚拟机的字节码，
that translation might be to machine codes. It might be to a bytecode for a virtual machine.
也可能是另一种高级编程语言。
It might be to another high level programming language. Well
这就是这节课的内容, 下节课我们会讲到这
that's it for this lecture, and next time we'll pick up here and talk about these
五个阶段的更多细节。
five phases in more detail.